This work makes two linked contributions.
First, it distills key mechanisms of adaptation in
biological systems,
with a special focus on metaplasticity and
homeostatic regulation,
plus inhibition and forgetting.
Second,
it proposes concrete avenues to incorporate these
features into the self-optimization
model and Hopfield networks more broadly
by making the learning rate adaptive with respect
to synaptic weights or the energy landscape,
by enhancing modular structure, and by changing the
activation rule.
The aim is deep learning tools that recapitulate
the advantages of biological systems
and can plausibly model living and adaptive systems
across levels of complexity.